Register of the Walther Schevenels Papers, 1901-1986
Hoover Institution Archives
Walther Schevenels Papers,
1901-1986
77056
Schevenels, Walther, 1894-1966
19 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box (8.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, speeches, writings, notes, bulletins, interviews, pamphlets, clippings, and printed matter, relating to European and international trade unions, the labor movement in Europe, communism in the labor movement, and the post-World War II European Recovery Program.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
International Confederation of Free Trade Unions; International Federation of Trade Unions; Labour and Socialist International; World Federation of Trade Unions; Labor movement--Europe; Trade-unions; Trade-unions--Europe; Belgium; Europe; Reconstruction, 1939-1951--Europe; Trade-unions and communism.; Communism
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
1894 November 11 Born, Belgium
1921-1924 Secretary, Federation of Metalworkers, Antwerp, Belgium
1924 General Secretary, Provincial Federation of Metalworkers, Antwerp
1924-1929 Lecturer, National Labor College, Uccle-Brussels and Popular University Extension, Antwerp
1925 Executive member, Socialist Party; Honorary Director, Cooperative Union, Antwerp; Secretary, Provincial Parliament, Antwerp
1929-1930 Assistant General Secretary, International Federation of Trade Unions, Amsterdam
1930-1945 General Secretary, International Federation of Trade Unions, Amsterdam, Paris, London
1945-1949 Assistant General Secretary, World Federation of Trade Unions, Paris. Resigns in dispute with Communists, 1949
1949-1951 Secretary, Trade Union Advisory Committee for the European Recovery Program (Marshall Plan)
1951-1966 General Secretary, European Regional Organization of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, Brussels
1924 Author, Summarized Technology of Metal Industry and Trade Union Administration
1926 Author, Elementary Economic Principles
1956 Author, Forty-five Years: International Federation of Trade Unions
1966 March 6 Died, Brussels
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1941-1966. (Box 1)
  Bank book, biographies, clippings, death notice, delegate mandate, financial records and correspondence, insurance correspondence, list of articles, travel documents, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1944-1965. (Boxes 2-3)
  Letters arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Includes some letters neither to nor from Walther Schevenels
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1940-1965. (Boxes 4-5)
  Articles, notes, speeches and related correspondence arranged chronologically by title
- INTERNATIONAL FEDERATION OF TRADE UNIONS (IFTU), 1901-1945. (Boxes 6-11)
  Circulars, clippings, correspondence, financial statements, membership list, minutes, press releases, publications, reports and statutes relating to Schevenels's tenure as General Secretary of the IFTU. Includes minutes of the Board of Trustees, which disposed of the IFTU's affairs following its dissolution in 1945
- WORLD FEDERATION OF TRADE UNIONS (WFTU), 1945-1956. (Boxes 12-14)
  Clippings, constitution, correspondence, declarations, minutes, publications, reports and speech relating to Schevenels's position as Assistant General Secretary of the WFTU, successor organization to the IFTU
- EUROPEAN RECOVERY PROGRAM (ERP), TRADE UNION ADVISORY COMMITTEE (Box 15)
  Correspondence and press release relating to Schevenels's position as Secretary of the Trade Union Advisory Committee of the ERP
- EUROPEAN REGIONAL ORGANIZATION (ERO) OF THE INTERNATIONAL (Box 15)
  Clippings, constitution, correspondence, manifestos, memoranda, minutes, notes, policy statements, press releases, proceedings, publications, questionnaires, reports and resolutions relating to Schevenels's position as General Secretary of the European Regional Organization of the ICFTU
- SUBJECT FILE, 1940-1967. (Boxes 16-19)
  Bulletins, chronology, clippings, minutes, notes, obituaries, pamphlets, paper, political cartoons, press release, program, publications, reports and speech arranged alphabetically by subject
- CARD FILE, n.d. (Box 20)
  Cards with addresses of correspondents. Unsorted
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1941-1966
  - Bank book (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Biographies. Includes correspondence (Folder 2)
  - Clippings (Folder 3)
  - Death notice (Folder 4)
  - Delegate mandate, World Federation of Trade Unions, 1947 (Folder 5)
  - Financial records and correspondence (Folder 6)
  - Insurance correspondence (Folder 7)
  - List of articles written by Schevenels. Includes program mentioning speaking engagement (Folder 8)
  - Subject file
    - Controversy involving objections by American Federation of Labor to Schevenels's appointment as Secretary, Trade Union Advisory Committee, European Recovery Program, 1949
      - Clippings (Folder 9)
      - Correspondence. Includes letter to editor, Neue Volkszeitung, New York (Folder 10)
    - Property in France. Affidavits and correspondence concerning disposition of Paris apartment, 1949 (Folder 11)
  - Travel documents (Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 13)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1944-1965
  - General, A-Z (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - Unidentified (Folder 2)
  - Ayusawa, Iwao, 1947 (Folder 3)
  - Becu, Omer, 1948-1964 (Folder 4)
  - Berman, H., 1947 (Folder 5)
  - Bernasconi, Giacomo, 1947-1948 (Folder 6)
  - Biossac, 1945. Includes letter to mayor of Perignanas, France (Folder 7)
  - Blum, Leon, 1941-1948. Includes letters from Hans Rottgen and Peter Schattner (Folder 8)
  - Bock, Georges, 1955 (Folder 9)
  - Bolz, Robert, 1948. Includes letter to Charles Laurent (Folder 10)
  - Bondy, Paul, 1947. Includes letters to Ehni and Unionsdruckerei Bern (Folder 11)
  - Born, Paula, 1947-1948. Includes letters to David Dubinsky, William Green and Philip Murray (Folder 12)
  - Bracops, Joseph, 1947-1948 (Folder 13)
  - Cahan, John Flint, 1960. Includes obituary (Folder 14)
  - Chevins, Hugh, 1948-1962 (Folder 15)
  - Citrine, Sir Walter, 1947-1962. Includes letter from Citrine to F. P. Somogyi (Folder 16)
  - Cope, Elmer, 1948-1953 (Folder 17)
  - Dallas, George, 1954 (Folder 18)
  - Darvall, Frank, 1958 (Folder 19)
  - Deakin, Arthur, 1947 (Folder 20)
  - Depaepe, Emile, 1947 (Folder 21)
  - Derkow, Willi, 1947-1957 (Folder 22)
  - Elliott, C. A., 1948 (Folder 23)
  - Erdmann, Elisabeth, 1947-1948 (Folder 24)
  - Franz, Novy, 1945 (Folder 25)
  - Gay, Helene and Maurice, 1947 (Folder 26)
  - Georgiades, G. A., 1961-1964 (Folder 27)
  - Germer, Adolph, 1946-1963. Includes letters to Germer from Ernest Untermann (Folder 28)
  - Gherman, Eftimie, 1948. Includes letter to Richard Eldridge (Folder 29)
  - Gordon, Sir Archibald, 1957-1958 (Folder 30)
  - Gottfurcht, Hans, 1947 (Folder 31)
  - Gros, Andre, 1958-1962 (Folder 32)
  - Hernandez, Alonso, 1948-1949 (Folder 33)
  - Jouhaux, Leon, 1948-1951 (Folder 34)
  - Kieffer, Alice, 1948. Includes letters to Richard Eldridge (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - Kienzel, Hans, 1954 (Folder 2)
  - Kissane, Helen, 1948-1949 (Folder 3)
  - Klenner, Fritz, 1959-1965 (Folder 4)
  - Kolarz, Shura, 1947-1963 (Folder 5)
  - Krane, Patsy, 1961. Includes correspondence with Michael Ross (Folder 6)
  - Krier-Becker, Lily, 1949 (Folder 7)
  - Kupers, Evert, 1946-1948 (Folder 8)
  - Kuppers, Heinz, 1960 (Folder 9)
  - Launay, Jacques de, 1959-1962 (Folder 10)
  - Lecache, Bernard, 1947 (Folder 11)
  - Lecomte, Marie-Therese, 1956. Includes letter to G. Glisenti (Folder 12)
  - Lende, C. van der, 1946 (Folder 13)
  - Lippmann, Max, 1947 (Folder 14)
  - Luck, Kate, 1948 (Folder 15)
  - Marchal, M., 1955-1964 (Folder 16)
  - Martin, Harry, 1951 (Folder 17)
  - Martinez, Esteban, 1948. Includes correspondence with George Tomlinson (Folder 18)
  - Millar, James, 1949-1965 (Folder 19)
  - Muts, Henri, 1948. Includes letters to Corley Smith and Van Groningen (Folder 20)
  - Nemecek, Vaclav, 1948 (Folder 21)
  - Peyer, Karl, 1948 (Folder 22)
  - Pryce, Roy, 1965 (Folder 23)
  - Rabec, Jacques, 1958. Includes correspondence with Alain Le Cunff and Lucien Radoux (Folder 24)
  - Renard, Andre, 1947-1948 (Folder 25)
  - Rens, Jef, 1945-1948 (Folder 26)
  - Reventlow, Rolf, 1952-1965. Includes letter by Suzanne Reventlow to World Health Organization (Folder 27)
  - Rimensberger, E. F., 1946-1948 (Folder 28)
  - Robens, Alfred, 1958-1959 (Folder 29)
  - Roemers, Dirk, 1954 (Folder 30)
  - Ross, Michael, 1949 (Folder 31)
  - Rottgen, Hans, 1946-1965. Includes correspondence between Rottgen and Robert J. Alexander (Folder 32)
  - Salis, Charles de, 1948 (Folder 33)
  - Saposs, David, 1949-1958 (Folder 34)
  - Schattner, Peter, 1947-1948 (Folder 35)
  - Scheugenpflug, Otto, 1958-1959 (Folder 36)
  - Schevenels, Alain, 1957 (Folder 37)
  - Schevenels, Armando, 1948 (Folder 38)
  - Schevenels, Conrad, 1946-1961. Includes correspondence with Kenneth Peacock and Vincent Tewson (Folder 39)
  - Schevenels, G., 1958-1960 (Folder 40)
  - Schevenels, Jules, 1948 (Folder 41)
  - Schevenels, Sophie, 1942-1952. Includes letters to Sophie Schevenels from Pearl Davis and Lydia Liporsky (Folder 42)
  - Schiefer, Marie, 1956 (Folder 43)
  - Schiff, Victor, 1948 (Folder 44)
  - Schneiter, 1948 (Folder 45)
  - Schuil, Jan, 1947-1949 (Folder 46)
  - Seaward, E. H., 1957 (Folder 47)
  - Sergent, Rene, 1960 (Folder 48)
  - Simpson, Smith, 1947 (Folder 49)
  - Teltscher, Frans, 1947 (Folder 50)
  - Teltscher, Richard, 1947-1961 (Folder 51)
  - Thijs, Victor, 1946-1947 (Folder 52)
  - Twerenbold, Rosalie, 1947. Includes correspondence with Rene Meyer (Folder 53)
  - Ustinov, J., 1947 (Folder 54)
  - Wauters, Arthur, 1943 (Folder 55)
  - Weisz, Morris, 1954 (Folder 56)
  - Woodcock, George, 1947-1960 (Folder 57)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1940-1965
  - "The Continental Trade Unions and European Unity," Plebs, n.d. Printed copy (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - "Dates historiques principales du mouvement syndical international," n.d. Holograph (Folder 2)
  - "From OEEC into OECD," n.d. Printed copy (Folder 3)
  - "Der IGB nach Sassenbach," n.d. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - "Le mouvement syndical ouvrier en Europe," n.d. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - Notes for speeches, n.d. Holograph and typescript (Folder 6)
  - Notes on labor history, n.d. (Folder 7)
  - Notes on various subjects, n.d. (Folder 8)
  - "Les objectifs d'action des forces syndicales democratiques en Europe occidentale," n.d. Typescript (Folder 9)
  - Radio interview, Hessischer Rundfunk and RIAS-Berlin, n.d. Typescript (Folder 10)
  - "Reprise de la collaboration des syndicats avec l'O.C.D.E.," n.d. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - "Les travailleurs et la campagne de productivite," n.d. Mimeograph (Folder 12)
  - Statement to International Committee, Trades Union Congress, London, 1940 December 5. Mimeograph (Folder 13)
  - "L'Amerique entre dans la bataille des democraties contre les dictatures," 1942. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - "Some Facts about Connections and Cooperation between German Landowners, Finance, Industry and National Socialism," 1942 August 27. Typescript (Folder 15)
  - Eulogy for Edo Fimmen, The International Transport Workers' Journal, 1942 November-December. Typescript drafts, printed copy and correspondence (Folder 16)
  - "The I.F.T.U. in the War," International Socialist Forum, 1943. Typescript article and correspondence (Folder 17)
  - "10 Years Nazi Dictatorship," 1943 January 29-30. Holograph notes (Folder 18)
  - "Basis for World Federation of Trade Unions," 1945 February 13. Speech, World Trade Union Conference, London. Mimeograph (Folder 19)
  - "A la memoire de Pierre Krier," 1947 February 1. Typescript article and correspondence (Folder 20)
  - "Der amerikanische Hilfsplan fur Europa," 1948 January 19. Typescript (Folder 21)
  - Notes for speech, 1948 March 14, Saarbrucken, Germany. Holograph (Folder 22)
  - "Die Arbeiterschaft - deutsche und europaische - muss fur die Internationalisierung der Ruhr sein," 1949 January 11. Typescript (Folder 23)
  - Speech, 1950. Printed copy (Folder 24)
  - Radio address about Marshall Plan, 1950 March 24. Typescript (Folder 25)
  - Interview with Stanley H. Kapner, 1950 November. Typescript (Folder 26)
  - Eulogy for Fritz Tarnow, 1951 October 27, Frankfurt. Notes, typescript speech and funeral program (Folder 27)
  - "Un nouveau premier mai," 1953. Typescript (Folder 28)
  - Speech to AFL Congress, Norway, 1953 April. Typescript (Folder 29)
  - "Message du premier mai aux travailleurs soumis au joug sovietique," 1954 April 16. Typescript article and accompanying letter (Folder 30)
  - Notes for speech?, 1954 October 6. Holograph (Folder 31)
  - Notes for interview, Radio Wien, 1955 May 24. Holograph and typescript (Folder 32)
  - Forty-five Years: International Federation of Trade Unions, 1956
    - Research notes (Folder 33)
    - Table of contents, bibliography and list. Printed copy (Folder 34)
    - Advertising copy. Typescript (Folder 35)
    - Reviews (Folder 36)
    - Correspondence
      - 1952 (Folder 37)
      - 1957-1965 (Folder 38)
    - French translation
      - Typescript of preface and fragments (Folder 39)
      - Proofs of photos and notes (Folder 40)
    - German translation and preface for projected expanded version, "100 Jahre internationale Gewerkschaftsbewegung." Typescript and mimeograph (Folder 41)
  - Questions for radio interview, 1956 July 5. Typescript (Folder 42)
  - "CISL-ORE et ses problemes," 1956 September 19. Speech, Internationale du Personnel des Postes, Telegraphes et Telephones (PTTI), Vitznau, Switzerland. Notes (Folder 43)
  - "Les syndicats, l'automation et l'Europe," 1956 November 9. Typescript (Folder 44)
  - Speech, 1956 December 18. Notes and letter (Folder 45)
  - "La Grande-Bretagne dans la zone de libre echange: points de vue des syndicats britanniques," 1957 March 2. Typescript (Folder 46)
  - "L'integration europeenne et la Grece," 1957 April 13. Typescript (Folder 47)
  - Speech, Stuttgart, Germany, 1957 May 1. Notes and flier (Box 5., Folder 1)
  - Speech to AFL Congress, Norway, 1957 May 5. Typescript (Folder 2)
  - "The European Common Market and the Free Trade Area," Free Trade World,1957 May. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 3)
  - Speech, Radio Tunis, 1957 July 8. Notes (Folder 4)
  - "Les syndicats libres de l'Europe," Associations Internationales, 1957 September. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 5)
  - "L'automation et ses repercussions sociales, y compris la formation et la readaptation professionnelles," Silicates Industriels, 1957 November. Printed copy (Folder 6)
  - "Les syndicats ouvriers devant l'automation," 1957 December 13. Speech, Journees Internationales d'Information sur les Implications Economiques et Sociales de l'Automation, Namur, Belgium. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 7)
  - "European Political Unity," 1958 June 16. Speech, Trade Union Leaders' Training Conference, Greek General Confederation of Labor, Chalkis, Greece. Typescript outline, notes, correspondence and speeches by others (Folder 8)
  - "Droits et responsabilites des syndicats sur le plan international," 1958 September 22-October 4. Lecture, European Trade Union Course, Fiesole, Italy. Mimeographed outline (Folder 9)
  - "Les syndicats sont-ils finis?," 1958 September 22-October 4. Lecture, European Trade Union Course, Fiesole, Italy. Typescript (Folder 10)
  - "Trade Unions and United Europe," 1958 November 8. Lecture, Workers' Educational Association, Birmingham, England. Clippings, correspondence and fliers (Folder 11)
  - "International Trade Unionism Today," 1958 November 9. Lecture, Workers' Educational Association, Leicester, England. Correspondence and flier (Folder 12)
  - "Way Study Session for Youth," 1959 March 29. Lecture, Geneva. Typescript (Folder 13)
  - Speech to DSF Congress, Copenhagen, 1959 May 13. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - "Retrospection of Efforts to Achieve European Unification," 1959 September 2-11. Speech, European Trade Union Course, London. Holograph notes and mimeographed outline (Folder 15)
  - "L'O.R.E., ses taches en Europe et ses relations avec les institutions intergouvernementales," 1959 November 26. Speech, Ecole des Cadres Generale, Blankenberge, Belgium. Typewritten outline (Folder 16)
  - "The Six, the Seven and the Seventeen," IUSY Survey, 1960. Printed copy (Folder 17)
  - "Free Trade Unions' Role in International Organisations," 1960 August 1. Lecture, Internationale du Personnel des Postes, Telegraphes et Telephones (PTTI) 4th Education Course, Worcester, England. Notes and schedule (Folder 18)
  - Response to questions on agricultural problems, forum of L'Europeen, 1960 September 12. Typescript (Folder 19)
  - Speech on European integration, Unilever N.V., Rotterdam, 1960 October 10. Outline and letter (Folder 20)
  - "Le mouvement syndical international et la regionale europeenne," 1960 October 31-November 10. Lecture, European Trade Union Seminar, Freinberg, Germany. Mimeographed outline (Folder 21)
  - Speech on European integration, 1961 June 28. Notes and correspondence (Folder 22)
  - "Point de vue d'un syndicaliste," 1961 October 17. Speech, Societes du Groupe Unilever, Brussels. Notes, clipping and program (Folder 23)
  - Eulogy for Hendrik Oosterhuis, 1962 January 26, Amsterdam. Notes and funeral program (Folder 24)
  - "Atlantic Cooperation: Road to European Unity?," 1962 February 2. Typescript (Folder 25)
  - "Droits de l'homme et syndicalisme libre international," 1962 March 17. Speech, Week-end de Formation Syndicale pour Travailleurs Espagnols de la Region de Bruxelles, Tremelo, Belgium. Notes, research material, program and correspondence (Folder 26)
  - "European Unification and the Trade Unions," 1962 March 28. Lecture to Europe House, London. Printed summary and correspondence with Val Schur of Britain in Europe (Folder 27)
  - Speech to Deutscher Gewerkschaftsbund (DGB) Youth Conference, 1962 April, Berlin. Typescript (Folder 28)
  - "L'O.R.E., sa structure et ses taches en Europe," 1962 April 18. Typescript (Folder 29)
  - "Einige geschichtliche Gesichtspunkte der Tatigkeiten der Gewerkschaften auf dem Gebiet der Arbeiterbildung," 1962 May 21-30. Lecture, European trade union seminar, Strasbourg, France. Mimeographed outline (Folder 30)
  - "The Trade Unions and the Common Market," 1962 June 27. Speech, National Council of Labour Colleges, Huizingen, Belgium. Notes and correspondence (Folder 31)
  - Notes for lecture, 11th International Summer School, Offentliche Dienste Transport und Verkehr, Mosbach, Germany. Includes typescript list of participants (Folder 32)
  - "The European Regional Organization and the Young Workers," 1963 May 31. Typescript article and accompanying letter (Folder 33)
  - "Rolle und Aufgaben der Gewerkschaften beim Streben nach der Vereinheitlichung Europas," 1963 August 2. Lecture, 12th International Summer School, Offentliche Dienste Transport und Verkehr, Mosbach, Germany. Typescript outline, mimeographed outline and schedule (Folder 34)
  - "De E.R.O. zijn taken in Europa en zijn betrekkingen met de intergouvernementele instellingen," 1965 April 21. Speech, Nederlands Verbond van Vakverenigingen (N.V.V.), Amsterdam. Typed outline, mimeographed summary and correspondence (Folder 35)
- INTERNATIONAL FEDERATION OF TRADE UNIONS (IFTU), 1901-1945
  - General. Outline of lecture by R. Chamberion on the history of the IFTU, 1947 January 23 (Box 6., Folder 1)
  - Circulars, including lists of addressees (Folder 2)
  - Clippings (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. Includes correspondence of Schevenels's assistant, George Stolz
    - General
      - 1940 (Folder 4)
      - 1941 (Folder 5)
      - 1942 (Folder 6)
      - 1943 (Folder 7)
      - 1944 (Folder 8)
      - 1945 (Box 7., Folder 1-2)
    - Board of Trustees
      - 1947-1950 (Folder 3)
      - 1951 (Folder 4)
  - Financial statements (Folder 5)
  - Membership list of Secretariat (Folder 6)
  - Minutes
    - General Council, 1933-1945. Includes minutes of Executive Committee and notes by Schevenels (Folder 7)
    - Emergency International Trade Union Council, 1942-44. Includes correspondence and notes by Schevenels
      - General (Box 8., Folder 1)
      - Committee I, 1942-1943. Includes reports (Folder 2)
      - Committee II, 1942-1943. Includes reports (Folder 3)
    - Board of Trustees, 1945-1951 (Folder 4)
  - Press releases (Folder 5)
  - Publications
    - Brochures and pamphlets (Folder 6-7)
    - Bulletin, 1939 (Box 9., Folder 1)
    - Triennial report, 1937 (Folder 2-3)
  - Reports, 1933-1945. Includes correspondence, reports submitted to IFTU by national representatives and report by Schevenels on Italian trade unions, 1944 (Folder 4)
  - Statutes (Folder 5)
  - Subject file relating mainly to the IFTU's activities during World War II in support of exiled trade unionists, political refugees and resistance movements
    - France
      - Circulars, financial reports, memos, reports and statutes of le Centre Syndical Francais, affiliate of IFTU (Box 10., Folder 1)
      - Correspondence. Includes many letters to and from officials of la Confederation Generale du Travail (CGT) and le Centre Syndical Francais
        - 1940 (Folder 2)
        - 1941 (Folder 3)
        - 1942 (Folder 4)
        - 1943 (Folder 5)
        - 1944 (Folder 6)
      - Leaflets distributed in occupied France (Folder 7)
      - Notes by Schevenels (Folder 8)
    - Germany
      - Correspondence, 1940-1943. Includes notes by Schevenels (Folder 9)
      - Resolution of IFTU on Jews in Germany (Folder 10)
    - Radio broadcasts (mainly BBC) to Germany and occupied Europe
      - Clippings (Folder 11)
      - Correspondence. Includes minutes of Joint Council of the Three Internationals (Box 11., Folder 1)
      - Notes by Schevenels and others (Folder 2)
      - Transcripts of radio broadcasts by Schevenels and others (Folder 3)
    - Refugee assistance. Correspondence, 1942-44. Includes notes by Schevenels, lists of political refugees and reports by aid organizations (Folder 4)
    - Trade union conferences
      - Amsterdam, 1921. Resolutions (Folder 5)
      - London and Paris, 1945
        - Clippings (Folder 6)
        - Minutes, memoranda and notes by Schevenels, speech by Walter Citrine (Folder 7)
- WORLD FEDERATION OF TRADE UNIONS (WFTU), 1945-1956
  - Clippings
    - 1945 (Box 12., Folder 1)
    - 1946 (Folder 2)
    - 1947 (Folder 3)
    - 1948 (Folder 4-5)
    - 1949 (Folder 6)
    - 1950-1956 (Folder 7)
  - Constitution, 1945 (Folder 8)
  - Correspondence
    - 1945 (Folder 9)
    - 1946 (Folder 10)
    - 1947 (Folder 11)
    - 1948 (Folder 12)
  - Declarations by Executive Bureau (Box 13., Folder 1)
  - Minutes
    - Executive Bureau. Includes agendas and notes by Schevenels
      - 1945 (Folder 2)
      - 1946 (Folder 3-4)
      - 1948 (Folder 5)
      - 1949 (Folder 6)
    - Secretariat. Agenda and notes by Schevenels, 1948 (Folder 7)
  - Publications (Folder 8)
  - Reports